Thank you.
Don't you think, sir,
considering what is happening in the world,
in India, in Europe and in America,
the general degeneration in literature, in art,
and especially in the culture,
deep culture,
cultural sense, in the sense religion,
there is a traditional approach,
a mere acceptance of authority, belief,
which is not really the religious spirit.
Seeing all this, the confusion,
the great misery,
the sense of infinite sorrow,
any observant and most serious people
would say that society cannot possibly be changed
except only when the individual,
the individual,
the human being,
really transforms himself radically,
that is, regenerates himself fundamentally.
And the responsibility of that depends on the human being,
not on the mass or on the
priest or on a church or a temple
or mosque or whatever it is,
but on a human being who is aware
of this enormous confusion,
politically, religiously, economically,
in every direction.
There is such misery,
such unhappiness.
And when you see that,
it is a very serious thing
to ask oneself,
whether a human being like oneself or another,
whether he can really deeply undergo
a radical transformation.
And when that question is put to him,
and when he sees his responsibility
in relation to the whole,
then perhaps we can discuss
what relationship has knowledge
and time in the transformation of man.
I quite follow.
We need then to lay some groundwork
in order to move into the question itself.
Yes, because most people
are not concerned with the world at all.
Most people are not concerned seriously
with the events, with the chaos,
with the mess in the world at present.
They are only concerned very superficially
with the problem of energy,
the problem of pollution, and so on,
such superficial things.
But they are really not deeply concerned
with the human mind,
the mind that is destroying the world.
Yes, yes, I quite follow.
What you have said places in a very cardinal way
the radical responsibility on the individual as such,
if I have understood you correctly.
There are no five-year plans
that we can expect to help us out.
The word individual really is not the correct word
because individual, as you know, sir, means
undivided, indivisible,
in himself.
But human beings are totally fragmented,
therefore they are not individuals.
They may have a bank account, a name, a house,
but they are not really individuals in the sense
a total, complete, harmonious whole,
unfragmented.
That's really what it means to be an individual.
Would you say then that to move or make passage,
or perhaps a better word simply would be change,
since we are not talking about time,
from this fragmented state
to one of wholeness,
could be regarded as a change
in the level of the being of the person?
Yes.
Could we say that?
But you see again the word whole implies
not only sanity,
health,
and also the word whole means holy,
h-o-l-y.
All that is implied in that one word, whole.
And human beings are never whole,
they are fragmented,
they are contradictory,
they are torn apart by various desires.
So when we talk of an individual,
the individual is really a human being
who is totally, completely whole,
sane, healthy, and therefore holy.
And to bring about such a human being
is our responsibility
in education, politically, religiously,
in every way.
And therefore it is the responsibility
of the educator, of everybody,
not just myself, my responsibility.
It is your responsibility as well as mine,
as well as his.
It is everyone's responsibility.
Absolutely, because we have created
this awful mess in the world.
But the individual is the one
who must make the start.
A human being.
Right.
Each human being,
whether it is a human being
or a politician,
or a businessman,
or just an ordinary person like me in the street,
it is our business as a human being
to realise the enormous suffering,
misery, confusion there is in the world.
And it is our responsibility to change all that.
Not the politicians,
not the businessmen,
not the scientists.
It is our responsibility.
When we say,
it is only our responsibility.
And we have two uses of the word individual now.
There is the general use of it,
meaning a quantitative measure.
Yes.
And then this qualitative reference
that we have simply needed,
it seems to me,
to discern as a possibility.
I am reminded again
of the statement that you made
that I quoted earlier,
that it is the responsibility of each human person.
Human being, yes.
Right.
Whether he is in India,
or in England,
or in America,
or wherever he is.
So we can't slip out of this by saying,
we have created this,
therefore we must change it.
No, no, no.
We get back to,
well, if the change is going to start at all,
it is going to be with each.
Yes, sir.
With each.
With each human being.
Therefore the question arises from that,
does a human being realise,
with all seriousness,
the...
his responsibility
not only to himself
but to the whole of mankind?
It wouldn't appear
so from the way things go on.
Obviously not.
Each one is concerned with his own little,
petty little selfish desires.
So,
responsibility implies
tremendous attention, care,
diligence,
not negligence as now it is going on.
Yes, I do follow that.
The word we that we used
in relation to each
brings about the suggestion of a relationship
which perhaps we could
pursue here a moment.
There seems to be something indivisible,
apparently, between
what we refer to by each
or the individual person
as the usage is usually construed,
seems to be an indivisible relation
between that
and what we call the whole,
which the individual doesn't sense.
Sir,
as you know, I have been
all over the world,
except behind the Iron Curtain
and the bamboo curtain,
I've been all over.
And I've talked, seen
dozens and thousands of people.
I've been doing this for fifty years
and more.
Human beings,
wherever they live,
are more or less the same.
They have their problems of sorrow,
problems of fear,
problems of livelihood,
problems of personal relationship,
problems of survival,
overpopulation,
and whether this enormous problem
of life
or the problem of death,
it's a common problem to all of us.
There is no eastern problem
and western problem.
The west has its particular civilisation
and the east has its own.
And human beings
are caught in this trap.
Yes, I follow that.
And they don't seem to be able
to get out of it.
They are going on and on
for millennia.
Therefore the question is,
how does he bring this about
as an each, as a one?
The word individual,
as you've just described it,
seems to me to have a relationship
to the word transform in itself.
And I'd like to ask you
whether you would agree in this.
It seems that many persons
have the notion that to transform a thing
means to change it utterly
without any relationship whatsoever
to what it is as such.
That would seem to ignore
that we are talking about a form
that undergoes a change,
which form itself still abides.
Yes, sir, I understand.
Otherwise the change would involve a loss.
So are we asking this question, sir,
what place
has knowledge
in the regeneration of man,
in the transformation of man,
in the fundamental, radical
movement in man?
What place has knowledge
and therefore time?
Is that what you are asking, sir?
Yes, yes I am.
Because either we accept
that a change that is a genuine change
means the annihilation of what preceded,
or we are talking about
a total transformation
of something that abides.
Yes. So let us look
at that word for a minute.
Good.
Revolution,
in the ordinary sense of that word,
means, doesn't it,
not an evolution,
a gradual evolution,
it is a revolution.
No, it doesn't mean that, right, I agree.
A revolution is generally meant
if you talk to a communist,
he wants to overthrow the government.
If you talk to a bourgeois,
he is frightened.
If you talk to an intellectual,
he has various
criticisms about revolution.
Now, revolution,
is either bloody,
or revolution in the psyche.
Outward or inner.
The outward is the inner.
The inner is the outward.
There is not the difference
between the outer and the inner.
They are totally related to each other.
Then this goes back
to what you mentioned earlier,
that there is no division,
even though intellectually,
you make a distinction here
between the I and the we.
That's right.
Yes, of course.
So, when we talk about change,
we mean not the mere bloody revolution,
physical revolution,
but rather the revolution
in the make-up of the mind.
Of each person.
Of human beings.
Right.
The way he thinks,
the way he behaves,
the way he conducts himself,
the way he operates,
he functions,
the whole of that.
Now, whether that psychological revolution,
not evolution in the sense,
gradualness...
No.
...what place has knowledge in that?
What place has knowledge
in something that occurs...
In the regeneration of man,
which is the revolution,
the inward revolution,
which will affect the outer.
Yes, which is not a gradual progress.
No, obviously.
No, right.
The gradual process is endless.
Exactly.
So we are talking about
an instant qualitative change.
Again, when you use the word instant,
it seems as though,
suddenly it is to happen.
I don't...
That's why I am rather hesitant
in using the word instant.
Instant.
We will go into it in a minute.
First of all, sir, let's be clear
what you and I are talking about,
if we may.
We see, objectively,
the appalling mess the world is in.
Right?
Yes.
The misery, the confusion,
the deep sorrow of man.
Oh, yes.
I can't tell you
what I feel when I go round the world,
the pettiness, the shallowness,
the emptiness of all this,
of the so-called Western civilisation,
if I may use that word,
into which the Eastern civilisation
is being dragged into,
and we are just scratching on the surface
all the time.
And we think the mere change on the surface,
a change in the structure
is going to do something enormous to human beings.
On the contrary, it has done nothing.
It polishes a little bit here and there,
but deeply, fundamentally,
it doesn't change man.
So, when we are...
when we are discussing change,
we must be, I think, fairly clear
that we mean the change in the psyche,
in the very being of human beings.
That is, in the very structure
and nature of his thought.
A change at the root.
At the root.
At the root itself.
And therefore, when there is that change,
he will naturally bring about a change in society.
It isn't...
Society first, individual or individual first,
it is the human change
which will transform the society.
They are not two separate things.
Now, I must be very careful
that I understand this precisely.
Yes.
I think I discern now
why in the statement you said,
which is not dependent on knowledge or time.
Yes.
Because when this person changes,
this each human being changes.
The change that begins in society
is a change that is in a non-temporal relationship
with the change in the each human being.
Yes, I follow.
After all, human beings have created this society.
By their greed, by their anger, by their violence,
by their brutality, by their pettiness,
they have created this society.
Precisely.
And they think by changing the structure
you are going to change the human being.
This has been the communist problem,
this has been the eternal problem.
That is, change the environment,
then you change man.
They have tried that in ten different ways
and they haven't done it,
succeeded in changing man.
On the contrary, man conquers the environment,
the structure.
So, if we are clear,
if we are clear that the outer is the inner,
the inner is the outer,
that there is not the division,
the society and the individual,
the collective and the separate human being,
but the human being is the whole.
He is the society,
he is the separate human individual,
he is the fact,
he is the matter which brings about this chaos.
Yes, I am following that very closely.
Therefore, he is the world and the world is him.
Yes.
Therefore, if he changes, everything changes.
If he doesn't change, nothing changes.
That's right.
I think this is very important
because we don't realise, I think,
this basic factor that we are the world
and the world is us,
that the world isn't something separate from me
and me separate from the world.
You are born in a culture,
Christian or Hindu or whatever culture you are born in,
you are the result of that culture.
And that culture has produced this world.
The materialistic world of the West,
if one can call it,
which is spreading all over the world,
destroying their own culture, their own traditions,
everything is being swept aside
in the wake of the Western culture.
嗯
And this culture has produced this human being.
And the human being has created this culture.
Exactly.
He has created the painting, the marvellous cathedrals,
the marvellous technological things,
going to the moon and so on, so on.
His human beings have produced it.
It's the human beings that have created
the rotten society in which we live.
It's the immoral society in which we live,
which human beings have created.
Oh yes, there is no way to know that.
And therefore the world is you, you are the world.
There is no other thing.
If we accept that, if we see that, not intellectually,
but feel it in your heart,
in your mind, in your blood,
that you are that, then the question is,
is it possible for a human being
to transform himself inwardly and therefore outwardly?
I am very concerned to see
this as clearly as I can
in terms of two texts that come to my mind
which, we could say, possess an inner meaning,
and because of this inner outer
thing that we have spoken about
in the divided approach that is made
to scripture. There's a tremendous irony here.
I'm thinking of that, to me, wonderful text
in St. John's Gospel, in the third chapter, which says,
and I'll try to translate
this as the Greek has it,
the one who is doing the
truth is coming to the light.
It isn't that he does the truth
and then later he comes to the light.
And it isn't that we could say from the pulpit,
I will tell you what the truth is.
If you do it, then you'll see the light.
Because we're back again to what you mentioned earlier,
the non-temporal relationship between the action,
which itself is the transformation,
and the marvellous vista
of understanding, which is not an if-then thing,
but is truly concurrent.
And the other one that I thought of,
that I was hoping you might agree in,
is saying the same thing,
so that I understand it well,
in terms of what you've said, is,
and again I'll try to translate
it as literally as I can,
God is love, and the one abiding,
in love,
is abiding in God, and God is abiding in him.
Of course.
I put the ing on all those words
because of the character of the language itself.
It doesn't read to...
one wouldn't want to translate
that for pulpit reading, perhaps,
but that's the real sense of it.
And this inging along gives the
feeling that there's an activity here.
Oh, of course.
That is not bound by temple relations.
It isn't a static state.
It isn't something you intellectually accept it
and leave it like that.
Then it's death, there is nothing in it.
Yes.
That's why...
You see, sir,
we have divided the physical world
as the East and the West.
We have divided religions, Christian religion,
and Hindu, Muslim, Buddhist.
And we have divided the world into nationalities
– the capitalist, the socialist,
the communist and the other people, so on.
We have divided the world,
and we have divided ourselves as Christians, non-Christians.
Yes.
We have divided ourselves into fragments,
opposing each other.
So where there is a division,
there is conflict.
Precisely.
I think that's a basic law.
Where there is a division, there is conflict.
But in terms of that word knowledge,
it appears that people believe, to start with,
that that division is there.
And they operate on that radical belief.
That's why I'm saying it's so important to understand
from the beginning in our talk, in our dialogue,
that the world is not different from me,
and I am the world.
It may sound rather very simplified, simplistic,
but it has got very deep fundamental meaning
if you realise what it means.
Not intellectually, but inwardly, the understanding of it.
Therefore there is no division.
The moment I say to myself,
and I realise that I am the world,
the world is me,
I am not a Christian, or
a Hindu, or a Buddhist, nothing.
I am a human being.
I was just thinking, when you were saying that,
how certain kinds of philosophical analysis
would approach that,
and in terms of the spirit of what you've said,
this really is almost a cosmic joke,
because on the one hand, as you said,
it might sound simplistic.
Some would say it is,
therefore we don't have to pay attention to it.
Others would say, well, it's probably
so much in want of clarity,
even though it's profound,
that it's some kind of mysticism out here.
And we're back and forth with the division again,
as soon as that happens. Again, that's right.
I do follow you.
So, if that is clear,
that there is that human mind
that the human mind has divided the world
in order to find its own security,
which brings about its own insecurity,
when one is aware of that,
then one must inwardly as well as outwardly
deny this division,
as we and they, I and you,
and the Indian and the European,
and the Communist,
you cut at the very root of this division.
Therefore, from that arises the question,
can the human mind,
which has been so conditioned for millennia,
can that human mind,
which has acquired so much knowledge
in so many directions,
can that human mind
change, bring about a regeneration in itself,
and be free to reincarnate now?
Now. Now. Yes.
That is the question.
That's the question.
Exactly. Reincarnate now.
It would appear from what you've said
that one could say that the vast amount
of represented knowledge,
an accretion of centuries,
is a discussion we've been having with ourselves,
regardless of which culture we're speaking about,
as a commentary on this division.
Absolutely.
Without really grasping the division,
it's a division itself.
And of course, since the division is infinitely divisible...
Of course. Why don't you divide? Go on, division.
Exactly. Then we can have tome after tome after tome,
libraries after libraries,
mausoleums of books without end,
because we're continually dividing the division.
That's right. Yes, I follow you.
And you see, that's why
culture is different from civilisation.
Culture implies growth.
Oh yes. Oh yes.
Now, growth in the flowering of goodness.
Lovely phrase. Lovely phrase.
That is culture.
The flowering of goodness. Real culture.
The flowering in goodness. You understand, sir?
Yes. And that doesn't exist.
We have civilisation.
You can travel from India
to America in a few hours.
You have better bathrooms, better this and better that,
and so on, with all the complications that it involves.
That has been the Western culture
which is absorbing the East now.
So, goodness is the very essence of culture.
Religion is the transformation of man.
Not all the belief, churches,
and the idolatry of the Christians or the Hindus.
That's not religion.
So we come back to the point,
if one sees all this in this world, observes it,
not condemn it or justify it, just to observe it,
then from that one asks,
man has collected such enormous information,
knowledge, and has that knowledge changed him into goodness?
You follow, sir? Oh, yes. I follow.
Into a culture that makes him
flower in this beauty of goodness.
It has not. No, it has not.
Therefore it has no meaning.
Excursions into defining goodness is not going to help us.
I mean, you can give explanations
one definition, but that's not...
definitions are not the reality.
No, of course not.
The word isn't the thing.
The description isn't the described.
Precisely.
So, we come back again.
Yes, yes, let's do.
Because I, personally,
I am tremendously concerned with this question.
How to change man?
Because I go to India every year,
for three months or five months,
and I see what is happening there,
and I see what is happening in Europe,
I see what is happening in this country, America,
and it is something...
I can't tell you what shock it gives me
each time I come to these countries.
The degeneration, the superficiality.
The intellectual concepts galore,
without any substance, without any basis,
or a ground in which the beauty of goodness,
of reality can grow.
Now, so, saying all that,
what place has knowledge in the regeneration of man?
That is the basic question.
That's our point of departure.
Departure. Good.
And the knowledge that we have pointed to so far,
that has emerged in our discussion,
is a knowledge which in itself
has no power to effect this transformation.
No, sir, but knowledge has a place.
Yes, I didn't mean that.
I mean what is expected of this knowledge
that we pointed to, that is accumulated in libraries,
is an expectation which it in itself cannot fulfil.
No, no.
I want to... now I must
go back to the word again,
the word knowledge.
What does it mean to know?
Well, I have understood the word
in a strict sense, this way.
Knowledge is the apprehension of what is.
But what passes for knowledge might not be that.
No, what is generally accepted as knowledge,
is experience.
Yes, what is generally accepted.
We'll begin with that, because that's what...
Right, let's begin with what is generally accepted.
Experience, which yields or leaves
a mark which is knowledge.
That accumulated knowledge, whether in the scientific world,
or in the biological world, or in the business world,
or in the world of the mind,
the...
the knowledge being is the known.
The known is the past.
Therefore knowledge is the past.
Knowledge cannot be in the present.
I can use knowledge in the present.
But it's funded from the past.
Yes, but it has its roots in the past.
Yes, I've asked...
Which means... that's very interesting,
because this knowledge which we have acquired,
about everything...
Yes.
You read any... I personally
don't read any of these books,
neither the Bhagavad Gita, Upanishads,
none of the psychological books, nothing.
I'm not a reader.
I have observed tremendously all my life.
Now, knowledge,
has its place.
Oh yes, yes.
Let's be clear.
Oh yes, in the practical order.
Practical, technological,
I must know where I'm going,
physically and so on, so on, so on.
Now, what place has that,
which is human experience as well as scientific knowledge,
what place has that in
changing the quality of a mind
that has become brutal, violent, petty, selfish,
greedy, ambitious and all the rest of that?
What place has knowledge in that?
Well, going back to the statement we began with,
namely that this transformation
is not dependent on knowledge,
then the answer would have to
be it doesn't have a place.
Therefore, let's find out
what are the limits of knowledge.
Yes, yes, of course.
Where is the demarcation,
freedom from the known?
Yes.
Where does that freedom begin?
Good.
You understand? Yes.
Now I know precisely the point at
which we are going to move from.
Where does that freedom begin?
Which is not dependent
on this funded accretion from the past.
That's right.
So, human mind is constructed on knowledge.
Yes.
It has evolved through millennia
on this accretion, on tradition, on knowledge.
Yes. It is there.
And all our actions
are based on that knowledge.
Which by definition must be repetitious.
Obviously. Of course.
And it is repetitious.
So, what place,
what is the beginning of freedom
in relation to knowledge?
May I put it this way, make myself clear?
Yes.
I have experienced something yesterday
that has left a mark.
That is knowledge.
And with that knowledge I meet next experience.
So,
the next experience is translated in terms of the old.
And therefore that experience is never new.
So, in a way, if I understand you correctly,
you are saying that the experience that I had yesterday,
that I recall...
Recollection, yes.
...recollection upon my meeting something new,
that appears to have some relationship to it,
I approach on the basis
of holding my previous knowledge up
as a mirror in which to
determine the nature of this new thing...
Of this, quite. ...that I have confronted.
Quite, quite. Yes.
And this could be a rather crazy mirror.
Generally it is.
So, you see, that is
what I mean. Yes, I follow.
Whether... where is the beginning,
or where is freedom in relation to knowledge?
Or is freedom something other
than the continuity of knowledge?
Must be something other.
Which means, if one goes into it very, very deeply,
it means the ending of knowledge.
Yes.
And what does that mean?
What does it mean
to end knowledge
whereas I have lived entirely on knowledge?
It means that immediately.
I mean, see what is involved in it, sir.
I met you yesterday,
and there is the image of you in my mind,
and that image meets you next day.
Yes. The image meets you.
The image meets you.
The image meets me.
And I have a dozen images, or a hundred images.
So, the image is the knowledge.
The image is the tradition.
The image is the past.
Now, can there be freedom from that?
If this transformation that you speak of is to happen,
is to come to pass, there must be.
Of course. Therefore, how is that?
That's probably... I mean, we can state,
but how is the mind, which thrives, acts, functions
on image, on knowledge, on the known,
how is it to end that?
How am I...
You know, take this very simply.
Take this very simple fact.
You insult me or praise me.
That remains a knowledge.
With that image, with that knowledge, I meet you.
I never meet you.
The image meets you.
Exactly.
Therefore there is no relationship between you and me.
Yes, because between us this has been interposed.
Obviously. Yes.
Therefore, how is that image to end?
Never to register.
You follow?
I can't depend on someone
else to end it for me.
Therefore, what am I to do?
How am I, how is this mind,
which is registering, recording all the time,
the function of the brain
is to record all the time,
how is it to be free of knowledge?
Is it...
When you have done some harm to me,
personally or collectively, whatever way,
you have insulted me, you have flattered me,
how is the brain not to register that?
If it registers, it is already
an image, it is a memory.
And the past then meets the present.
And therefore there is no solution to it.
Exactly.
I was looking up that word the other day
in a very good dictionary,
it is called tradition.
It means, of course, in the ordinary word,
is to give, hand over, give a cross.
But it also has another peculiar meaning,
not peculiar, from the same word, betrayal.
Oh yes, traduce. Traduce.
And in discussing in India this came out,
betrayal of the present.
In the living tradition, I betray the present.
Yes, I do see that.
Which is, knowledge betrays the present.
Which is, in fact, a self-betrayal.
That's right. Yes.
So, how is the mind, which functions on knowledge,
how is the brain, which is recording all the time,
to see the importance of recording,
and not let it move in any other direction?
That is, sir, let me
put it this way, very simply,
you insult me, you hurt me,
by word, gesture, by an actual act.
That leaves a mark,
a mark on the brain, which is memory.
Yes.
That memory is knowledge.
That knowledge is going to interfere
in my meeting you next time.
Obviously.
Now, how is the brain, and also the mind,
how is the brain to
record and not let it interfere
with the present?
Well, the person must, it seems to me,
take pains to negate.
No, no, see what is implied.
I know, but see how am I to negate it?
How is the brain, whose function is to record,
like a computer, it's recording.
I didn't mean to suggest that it negates the recording,
but it's the association, the translation of the recording
into an emotional complex.
That's just the point.
How is it to end this emotional response
when I meet you next
time, you who have hurt me?
That's the problem.
That's the place from which we, in the practical order,
in our relation to ourselves, must then begin.
Yes. Exactly.
There is an aspect of this,
that interests me very much,
in terms of the relation
between the theoretical and the practical.
Sir, to me theory has no reality.
Well, let me put it this way.
Theories have no importance to
a man who is actually living.
May I say what I mean by theory?
I don't think I mean what
you think I mean by it.
I mean theory in the
sense of the Greek word theoria,
spectacle, what is out there that I see.
And the word is therefore very closely related
to what you've been talking about in terms of knowledge.
And yet it is the
case that if we see something,
that something is registered to us in the mind,
in terms of a likeness of it,
otherwise we should have to become
it in order to receive it,
which in the material order would annihilate us.
It seems to me, if I followed you correctly,
that there is a profound confusion in one's relationship
to that necessity for the finite being,
and what he makes of it.
And insofar as he's making the wrong thing of it,
Right.
he is in desperate trouble,
and can only go on repeating himself,
and in such a repetition increasing despair.
Have I distinguished this correctly?
You see,
religion is based on tradition.
Religion is vast propaganda,
as it is now.
In India, here, anywhere, propaganda
of theories, of beliefs, of idolatry, worship,
essentially based on the acceptance of a theory.
Yes, yes.
Essentially based on an idea.
A statement, a postulate.
I mean, they are ideas put out by thought.
Right.
And obviously that's not religion.
So, religion as it exists now
is the very denial of truth.
Yes, yes, I'm sure I understand you.
Mm-hm.
And if a man, like me, wants to find out,
discover what the truth is,
he must deny the whole
structure of religion as it is.
Mm-hm.
Which is idolatry, propaganda, fear, division,
you're Christian, I'm Indian, all that nonsense.
Right.
And be a light to oneself.
Not in the vain sense of that word, or light,
because in darkness, the world is in darkness.
And a human being that has to transform himself
has to be a light to himself.
And light is not lit by somebody else.
So there's a point at which,
he must stop repeating himself.
Ah!
Is that correct? Correct, sir.
In a sense, we could
use the analogy perhaps from surgery.
Something that has been continuous is now cut.
Yes.
And cut radically.
Not just fooled around, but really cut.
Sir, we haven't time to fool around any more.
Exactly. The house is on fire.
At least I feel this enormously,
that things are coming to such a pass,
we must do something, each human being.
Not in terms of better houses, better security,
more this and that,
but basically to regenerate himself.
But if the person believes
that in cutting himself from this,
that he is a Christian, that he is killing himself,
then he is going to resist that idea, isn't he?
Of course, of course.
Therefore he has to understand
what his mind has created.
Therefore he has to understand himself.
So he starts observing.
Himself. Himself.
Which is the world. Yes.
Not learning five languages to be able to construe...
Ah, for God's sake, that's all I know.
No, no. Yes.
Or going to schools where you learn sensitivity
and all that rubbish.
The point that you are making, it seems to me,
is made also by the great Danish thinker, Kierkegaard,
who lived a very trying life in his own community,
because he was asking them, it seems to me,
to undertake what you are saying.
He was saying, look, if I go to seminary,
and I try to understand what Christianity is
by studying at my desk,
then what I am doing is appropriating something here,
but then when do I know
when I have appropriated it fully?
I shall never know that point,
therefore I shall forever appropriate it
and never do anything about it as such.
As a subject, the person who must risk the deed,
not the utterance of what someone has said before.
I don't know, of course.
So not simply thinking through
what someone has thought before,
but actually embodying the meaning
through the observation of myself in relation to that.
Quite, quite.
And that has always seemed
to me a very profound insight.
But one of the ironies of that is, of course,
in the academy we have an endless proliferation of studies
in which scholars have learned Danish
in order to understand Kierkegaard.
Oh, well.
And what they are doing is, to a large extent,
if I haven't misjudged the spirit
of much that I have read,
is simply perpetuate the very
thing he said should be cut.
I do have this very strong feeling that
profound change would take place in the academy,
of which you know I am a member.
A member, quite.
And the teacher were not only
to grasp this that you have said,
but take the risk of acting on it,
since if it isn't acted on,
if I have understood you correctly,
we are back again where we were.
We have toyed with the
idea of being valiant and courageous,
but then we have to think
about what is involved before we do,
and then we don't do.
Quite, quite.
We think and don't do.
Therefore, sir,
therefore, sir,
the word is not the thing.
The description is not the described.
And if you are not concerned with the description,
but only the thing, what is,
then we have to do something.
When you are confronted with what is, you act.
But when you are concerned with theories and speculations
and beliefs, you never act.
So there isn't any hope for this transformation,
if I have understood you correctly,
if I should think tomorrow,
I will never be myself.
That just sounds marvellous.
I am the world and the world is me,
while I go on thinking
that the description is the described.
There is no hope.
So we are speaking about a disease over here,
and we are speaking about something
that has been stated as the case.
And if I take what
has been stated as the case,
as the case,
then I am thinking the description is the described.
Of course.
It is like a man who is hungry.
Any amount of description of the right kind of food
and the beauty of the food will never satisfy him.
He is hungry, he wants food.
So all this implies, doesn't it, sir, several things.
First, can there be freedom from knowledge?
And knowledge has its place.
Yes.
Can there be freedom from the tradition as knowledge?
From the tradition as knowledge, yes.
Can there be freedom from this separative outlook,
me and you, we and they,
Christians and all this divisive
attitude or activity in life?
Those are the problems we have to...
That is what we must attend
to as we move through our dialogues.
So first, can the mind be free from the known?
I mean, not verbally, but actually.
But actually, yes.
I can speculate about what is freedom,
what is all the rest of it,
but see the necessity, the importance,
that there must be freedom from the known.
Otherwise life becomes repetitive,
continuous superficial scratching.
It has no meaning. Of course.
In our next conversation together,
I hope we can begin
where we have just left off.